http://www.cityofgp.com/city-government/bylaws-policies-procedures/freedom-information-and-protection-privacy

Jump to navigation
Notice | Face Coverings (Masks) MandatoryInformation | COVID-19 Response InformationeServicesContact Us
Search
Search Freedom of Information and Protection of Privacy
City GovernmentMayor & City CouncilCouncil MeetingsCity AdministrationWorking For The CityYouth Advisory CouncilBylaws, Policies, ProceduresBylawsPolicies & ProceduresFreedom of Information and Protection of PrivacyPetition Information PackageBudget & FinanceDisclosure of Wrongdoing and Reprisal Protection Program
FOIPThe Freedom of Information and Privacy Act (FOIP) ensures your right to know and access the City of Grande Prairie's general information and protects your right to privacy regarding your own personal information.Under the FOIP Act, the City is a local public body. Other examples of public bodies are school boards, post-secondary institutions, and health bodies.  FOIP legislation does not apply to the private sector.All information the City collects, records, and stores is subject to the legislation under FOIP.  Under the FOIP Act, you have a right to:request access to any and all records held by the City;access information the City has about you;request the City make corrections to your personal information;submit a request for an independent review of a FOIP issue with the Office of the Information and Privacy Commissioner.The City of Grande Prairie must:tell you why it is collecting information about you and how it will be used;only collect information that is absolutely necessary to operate a program, activity, or service;only collect information authorized by law and/or for law enforcement purposes;safeguard and protect all information that is collected, recorded and stored;only disclose information in accordance with the FOIP Act;make every effort to respond to an applicant openly, accurately and completely; andvoluntarily report to the Office of the Information and Privacy Commissioner when a breach poses a significant risk of harm.
What is personal information?Personal information is information that can be identified as belonging to a particular individual, some examples include your name, home or work address, home or work telephone number, age, sex, marital status, family status, educational, financial, employment or criminal history, including records where a pardon has been given, etc..  A more comprehensive list of what qualifies as Personal Information can be found in the FOIP Act under Section 1, (n), (i)-(ix).The City of Grande Prairie only has the authority to collect personal information under Section 33 of the FOIP Act.  Under this section, no personal information may be collected by or for a public body unless the collection is expressly authorized by an enactment of:a) Alberta or Canada (Section 33 (a));b) The information is collected for the purposes of Law Enforcement (Section 33 (b)), orc) The information relates directly to and is necessary for an operating program or activity of the public body.(Section 33 (c)). What is general information?General information is any information that is collected, recorded and stored in any manner in relation to all business operations, services and activities conducted by the City. How do you make a request to access information?To make a FOIP Request, determine if your request is general or personal in nature and complete the corresponding application form.  If you are unsure, contact the City of Grande Prairie's FOIP Coordinator, Valerie Norris-Kirk, at (780) 357-8716.Request to Access General Information FormRequest to Access Personal Information Form  Can you make a FOIP request on behalf of someone else?Yes.  When requesting records for another person, you will have to provide proof that you have the authority to act for that person.  Does the City have to tell you how your information will be used?Yes.  When collecting information about you, the City must do the following:tell you how your personal information will be used;tell you the authority for collecting the information;provide you with a name and contact for an employee who can assist you with any questions or concerns;collect your personal information directly from you, provided there are no exceptions under the FOIP Act. How do you ask for a correction to your personal information?Contact the service area that recorded the information and have them update your file.  If you are unable to have your Personal Information corrected in this way, fill out a Request to Access Personal Information form and specify what record you would like corrected.  What do you do if you find the City has breached your privacy?If you feel the City of Grande Prairie has breached your privacy,  contact the City FOIP Coordinator as soon as possible to initiate an investigation of the breach.   If you are not satisfied with the results of the investigation, you may submit an additional request for an investigation of the breach with the Information and Privacy Commissioner of Alberta. If you've been a victim of a crime, can you access City video surveillance?The City of Grande Prairie uses video surveillance for enhanced security of its facilities, to ensure the safety of its employees and as a means to discourage incidents of crime in public areas.   The use of video surveillance is restricted to periods of peak times when there is the potential for criminal activity and cameras are not directed or aimed into areas where people have an expectation of privacy.If you are a nearby business or homeowner that has experienced an incident of crime and requires video footage from one of our surveillance systems, you will have to make a Police Report with the RCMP.  As outlined in Video Surveillance in Public Areas (Procedure 805-1), RCMP must submit an Application for Law Enforcement Disclosure in order to access footage for their investigation.     Top Contact UsPermits & FormsParks & RecreationTaxation FAQCity MapsReports, Studies & PlanseServicesEvent CalendarWebsite Feedback
© City of Grande PrairieDisclaimerGoogle Translate is provided as a free tool to enhance the usability of the City of Grande Prairie website. As such, the City of Grande Prairie is not responsible for Google Translate™.
Neighbourhood Associations are registered societies that provide a central point of contact and a unified voice for the community.Learn MoreYou’ll find plenty of fun, free things to do in the City of Grande Prairie. Enjoy our beautiful parks and recreation spaces.Free ActivitiesDid you know that you can purchase fire pit permits, animal licenses and tax certificates online? You can even pay parking tickets.Explore eServicesCity Council establishes their vision and direction for the organization through the approval of a strategic plan.View the PlanWe have equipped all of our transit buses with real-time GPS technology so that you can easily find your ride at the click of a button.Routes & SchedulesMany energetic, business minded people are capitalizing on a business climate like no other.Economic ProfilePlanning on building a deck, shed, garage or other home improvement?Start Here
